Nikhil Thota

San Jose, CA 95126 • nikhil.thota@sisu.edu • + 1 (669)-677-1551 • LinkedIn • Github • Medium

Objective

Data Analyst with 4 years of experience and a Master's degree in Data Analytics from SJSU, specializing in Report generation, ETL/ELT pipelines, data migration and growth mindset. Built 20+ pipelines using SQL, Python, business intelligence (BI) tools, with a real touch of ML applications. Looking out for Summer Internships.

EDUCATION

- Master of Science in Data analytics, San Jose state university Jan 2023 - Expected. December 2024
- B.TECH IN COMPUTER SCIENCE AND ENGINEERING, IIIT VADODARA Aug 2015- Sept 2019

San Jose, CA

Gandhinagar, India

TECHNICAL SKILLS

- Databases: PostGreSQL, RDBMS, Neo4j, Redshift, BigQuery, MySQL
- Programming languages: R, Python, SQL, DAX, Hive SQL, Java (Object Oriented Programing Programming), PySpark
- Data Visualization Tools: Data Studio, Matlplotlib, Plotly, Power BI, Tableau, MicroStrategy, Grow (BI), Looker
- Workflow Tools: Airflow DAGS, DBT Cloud (ETL/ELT), Excel VBA
- Cloud: AWS S3, Redshift, DynamoDB, BigQuery, Google Cloud Buckets, Snowflake, Zeppelin, Databricks
- Mathematics: Statistics, Probability, Regression, Optimizations, Eigenvalues, eigenvectors, p-value, hypothesis testing
- Machine Learning: Keras, Tensorflow, Pandas, Numpy, Seaborn, scikit-learn, Requests, Data Analysis, Data Science

EXPERIENCE

Data Analyst | PharmEasy Dec 2021 - Jan 2023

- Orchestrated a 4% upswing in revenue by optimizing product listings accuracy, utilizing SQL,NER (NLP), CNNs for data driven rules on Product Catalog and implementing automation through Apache Airflow and SageMaker.
- Pioneered a transformative shift through cross-functional team collaborating, resulting in a remarkable 40% reduction in ad-hocs by building data pipelines, models, and dashboards with proficiency in Airflow, Presto, Redshift, and MicroStrategy.
- Delivered an impressive 8% boost in user conversion rates by analyzing real-time data seamlessly using Connectors (API), BigQuery, Google Analytics, DAX, and crafted compelling Power BI visualizations.
- Developed 8+ MicroStrategy Dashboards, & emailers in collaboration with demand business teams to aid in transformation of the firm's supply chain model from state based model to zone based model, thereby improving the demand by 15%.

Data Business Analyst | Saras Analytics

DEC 2020 - Dec 2021

- Executed Agile SDLC while Optimizing marketing strategies resulting in 10% sales uplift, by analyzing customer segments and leveraging SQL, DBT, and Looker for precision targeting across Google ads, Meta Ads, and other omni-channel platforms.
- Optimized & Refined BigData data models through Airflow, utilizing tools like DBT Cloud, S3, Python and SQL for ETL/ELT processes, enhancing efficiency and scalability across hive/presto systems reducing costs by 23%.
- Built Data Lakes on BigQuery, Snowflake, and Redshift, reducing data redundancy by an impressive 20% and elevating data transparency and accuracy from 40% to > 95% by employing data cleaning & transformation.
- Spearheaded the development of P/L dashboards for Amazon Sellers, resulting in a 20% cost reduction by integrating factors such as budget, forecasted sales, demand and COGS, providing key business insights using Compelling Tablea

Business Analyst | Capillary Technologies Pvt. Ltd

Jan 2019 - Dec 2020

- Delivered a 4x ROI as an intern by orchestrating data-driven campaign plans, collaborating cross-functionally with teams such as brand
 marketing, campaign delivery, finance, and legal, to execute successful campaigns in the retail industry.
- Mitigated fraud transactions by 17% in offline retail environments through the implementation of real-time, data-driven rules using SQL, Association rule mining, K-means clustering and predictive modeling.
- Drove a 20% increase in CRM growth by deploying advanced models incorporating RFM, Demand Forecasting, and Market Basket Analysis for customer retention, and cross-sell product analysis through real time campaigns using Ads.
- Retained 6+ clients by computing new metrics like CSI, NPS by leveraging 20+ SQL logics by incorporating inputs from Economics,
 Finance stakeholders and clients feedback to understand the fundamentals of the B2B and B2C systems.

PROJECTS

- BART, VTA DATA MODELLING: Employed a suite of tools including MySQL Workbench, Python, DBT, Neo4j, MongoDB, Mongo Atlas, BigQuery, GCP, AWS Glue, Kubernetes, and Flask in a comprehensive data modeling project for SJSU.

 Jan 2023 May 2023
- **Urban Audio Classification:** Lead a team of four in a research project focusing on comparative analysis of urban audio classifiers.

 Aimed to minimize use of labeled audio data. Vision Transformers (ViT) vs CNN variants, for SOTA results. **Sept 2023 Dec 2023**
- Polypharmacy effects: Developed a GCN using Node2Vec features for dr-dr interactions, predicting side-effects.

 Sept 2023 Dec 2023